[Music]
he
w
[Music]
good evening good day everybody and
welcome to the latest episode of the ask
AIT show I hope you're all doing great
so today I'm going to take questions
from the live chat from the live chat
that's going on on right now and that's
from which I will take the questions
lots happening in the world right now
Lots happened in the past so I'm sure
there's a lot of questions let me see
who all is there in the live stream I
can see ruir solanki sujit shanaga um
maheswari G Karan winter Rangers wolf PR
Paul zuang eung Raj animish aik benergy
Skywatch Alan J Victor gorov Singh moit
parashar pitos Rahul dun that only
1678 Sati Chans Shashank Kosik madav
chigurupati Ashish RSI Tanya Bater naita
Das Chan K ainash goami bitupan Bora
ratnesh Pia Arijit Viv Singh noil Sony
gorov Aurora random skull DBZ Natsu XY
ZM heray Milton chra netian Krishna mam
vun Singh Malik pan Kumar Singh s Satish
inia bries SK Dr suryakant AAR Chetan
aradya prachand
Anonymous geopolitical dub Milton
Chandra heray abishek 47 tagi jawaharlal
chavada P Sharma Krishna mitram anmol
pral Narayan Manisha cardoo shat an
Kumar biology KR trupti pel Fitness
science English practics gamer kishan
Jani nothing Sigma aninda bachar G
Priyanka jaala and everybody else so
with that done I'm going to stop
greeting you all individually there so
please go ahead ask your questions I'll
take as many as possible crazy brain I
can see hello so what are the questions
that we
have um winter Rangers wolf let's start
with this one give that India was once
divided into kingdoms do you think post
Independence division into States like
the European Union could have been a
better
development the European Union again is
like one country you see none of the
states are fully Sovereign they all have
some shared sovereignty pool sovereignty
and the real power the real decision-
making ability the policy framing
ability all that lies in
Brussels it resides in Brussels so and
and most of the EU States if not many of
them many of the EU States Nations are
members of NATO so that's where you have
pulled military capabilities so it's
kind of like the same thing and why
should we have what was the point what
would have been the point of us dividing
ourselves into separate Nations and then
creating a confederation or a union like
the
EU it makes sense to be together all of
us doesn't
it because at the end of the day we are
we are that would be the same kind of
thing actually with a little more
coherence in a nation in a nation state
so I think what we've done is right we
are a nation state we should aspire to
once again becoming a civilization State
and to well regain the status that we
historically always have
had
okay indrajit says when will India start
playing with the us the way they do with
us and PM is visiting the us next month
do you think he gonna do it do at once
what US diplomats are doing here with
the opposition the question is when will
India start playing with the US the play
the way the US plays with India what in
what way does the US play with India it
interferes in India's Internal Affairs
it did interfere in some ways in a
variety of ways in the 2024 general
elections by funding and promoting
various
influencers so-called influencers
so-called academic
so-called allegedly political parties by
by indulging in subnational diplomacy
what does the US do it it uh Engineers
regime change operations in India's
neighborhood these are the things that
the US does okay these are the things
that the US does I can I'm sure I can
list a whole lot more of what they do
they support uh a terrorist Nation like
Pakistan they funded and financed
Pakistani terrorism in India for decades
and much more that's what the US does
when can India first of all does India
want to play the same games with the US
certain things we just don't do right we
don't support
terrorism we don't do regime change
operations but let's say let's say
hypothetically India wanted to do that
hypothetically when could India be in a
position to do that well the answer is
very simple when India is India will be
in a position to do the same things when
India is as powerful as the US is right
now and when the US is as powerful as
India is right now the ations need to
reverse for that to happen so India
would need to become a global superpower
and in the US would have to become a
small Regional power then India would be
in a position to play those games long
long long far away kind of scenario okay
it it's it's not that easy I mean one
does understand that when the Americans
do these things you feel emotional and
you want to you want a response a strong
response from the government of India
and so on you can have a strong response
only if you have the actual capabilities
to withstand what the risk what the
ration could be like okay so there's a
big gigantic difference between words
and actions you make some rash
statements how harsh statements which
you cannot back up with hard power then
it's going to be bring a tremendous
amount of blowback upon you so every
nation should know what its power is
like what its standing is like in the in
the let's say the committee of Nations
and you have to behave and act in a way
that is proportional to the amount of
power you have in the global
Arena so India doesn't have a tremendous
amount of power right now yeah we have a
gigantic population largest population
in the world we have a large land area
land area Etc we have nuclear weapons
and we have certain other things but
compared to what the US has we are a
minuscule tiny little Nation
compared to the cumulative hard power of
the us so you don't play those games
when you are in the situation that India
is in right now okay that's simply how
it
works
um okay geopolitical dub says what's
cooking between bhat and China well
right now we don't know what's cooking
we don't quite know what is
cooking uh
ever since the regime change operation
that happened in uh East
Pakistan uh and of course also
considering what's happening in Burma
the Civil War that is has that has been
engineered and is currently raging in
Burma this overall situation which is
interconnected it affects India as well
as China and it has significantly uh
hampered China's PL plans for the
region and uh it doesn't make sense for
India in the long run to allow the
Americans to use us as a Pawn on the
geopolitical chessboard against
China the Chinese want Supremacy in Asia
and globally but they now hopefully
understand they are not going to achieve
Supremacy because of a number of reasons
first of all their economy is no no
longer growing that fast it's actually
not growing
well secondly there's a demographic
disaster that's it's pending it's coming
up for China the total fertility rate
has drastically declined it's around one
or
1.1 which is a disaster it's a
catastrophe China is going to get old
very rapidly the average age the median
age of the average person in China is
going to rise very rapidly so China is
going to get old before it gets Rich CH
is kind of on the lower fringes of the
middle income Nation
status and militarily it's not that
powerful sitting here in India clearly
China is way more powerful than India
it's about three times or almost four
times more powerful than India but
compared to the US China is that much CH
the Americans you people don't
understand how powerful the US military
machine is they can obliterate
China on
demand so China faces this
situation the Americans are squeezing
China from every side the Americans can
handle China's economy the two economies
are interdependent upon each other to a
large
extent uh China is encircled I mean if
you want to look at the map where's the
map we'll I'll show you the map in what
way is China encircled let me show you
in what way China is encircled
so yeah we have China to the west to the
east of China we have Japan which is an
American possession then you have South
Korea again an American possession then
you have the Philippines Indonesia
Malaysia Vietnam Thailand all of these
nations are kind of pro us even Vietnam
these days considering the bullying the
Chinese have been you know trusting upon
Vietnam if the Chinese change their
Vietnam policy the vietnames may become
more
friendly then there there are military
bases like Guam Etc which encircle China
and which allow the Americans to project
tremendous amount of power in the
region and then you have this nation
called India bat which the Chinese have
unnecessarily antagonized so China is
encircled completely encircled and now
with the developments in Bangladesh East
Pakistan and in Burma China is even
further
ened so that's a situation so it makes
sense for the Chinese to kind of play to
to to make amends with India and
cooperate with India because India
doesn't want war with China India
doesn't want a hostile situation with
China so and yet the situation is that
India cannot trust China right now the
way things stand India is not in a
position to trust China at all the
Chinese have played so many games that
we won't trust them so if India and
China were to let's say work together in
some way the Chinese will have to cons
will have to convince India that they
are worthy of trust now how do you do
that how can the Chinese convince India
that they are worthy of being trusted
that India can trust China there's only
one way of doing it demarcate the border
demarcate the Border Where's the border
this entire border that we see India CH
India Tibet border is actually
undemarcated if you are streaming or if
you're opening the map from Google Maps
from within India it will show you the
Indian version of the map if you go to
other countries and open the map from
there it'll show you a different version
of the B it'll show aai chin as part of
China or kind of with dashed lines and
all that it'll even try to claim that
arunachal Pradesh is disputed that's
what Google Maps will do even if I click
here it says unavailable unavailable
even though arunachal Pradesh is very
much part of India if I click within
Nepal it'll say whatever Place Nepal but
in arunachal it will it will say
unavailable so that's the deal so the
entire border is undemarcated thanks to
China the Chinese have steadfastly
refused to demarcate the India Tibet
border so if China wants barhat to feel
that we can trust China to a certain
extent they have to first Demar down
with India at the negotiating table and
rapidly demarcate the Border not just on
the map but also on the ground very
clear demarcation no ambiguity No No
Nonsense then
things may work going forward it's going
to be a very lengthy stepbystep
process okay and the chin the owners if
if the Chinese want cooperation with
India the owners is entirely on the
Chinese for this to work to make this
work so that's where we are I don't know
what's cooking what's bre Brewing
between India and China the Chinese seem
to be sending certain signals to India
if you look at their social media
signals Etc they are kind of playing
nice right now but I don't know what it
could indicate I think it's early days
maybe something may be Brewing behind
scenes behind closed doors but I Cann
speculate about that so that's where we
are Vis A India
and
China
okay Summit statement okay interesting
question how to achieve anything you
want how to stay motivated what are the
steps you are taking that look harders
than harder than others first of all you
have to understand and realize that you
cannot achieve everything that you
want that's going to be failures in
Life or you may be able to achieve
things but after multiple failures
that's also a possibility so there is
always the chance that you may not be
able to accomplish or achieve every
single thing that you
want that you have to realize first of
all and if you have to be okay with that
if you encounter a failure along the
Road you cannot let it break you you got
to dust it off and move on that's what
you have to do first of all you need so
what what what do I mean by that you
have to be resilient you need to be need
to be mentally really tough because life
is going to throw all kind of stuff at
you that's a guarantee okay the most
successful people are the ones who have
failed the
most and the most successful people they
haven't achieved everything they wanted
but they achieved great success at
whatever they famous for or they are
good at and so
on uh so how do you achieve with that
understood how do you achieve what you
let's say you let's say you have a
number of things that you want to
achieve so you first of all write it
down on a piece of paper I want to
achieve so so the this the the these
things in my
lifetime so first you make a list of
things that you want to achieve in your
lifetime then you ask yourself in what
time period do I want to achieve this
this this things the ones that can be
achieved before you can work on them
before for after you make a bucket list
you to you to ask yourself which are
non-negotiable and which are expendable
so you may have a whole bucket list of
78 things you want to achieve but then
you have to ask yourself are all of
these 78 things really worthwhile what
are the top three things I want to do in
my life or top five so you have to break
it down like that then you to have a
fiveyear wish list then a one year wish
list and then then you have to break
down that one year wish list of like the
top three things I want to achieve this
year into small actionable steps and
then you have to have a calendar write
it down on the calendar what I'm I going
to do this week this month today
tomorrow Etc and then you need to learn
how to manage time and so on so forth
and after doing all this you have to
execute as as hard and as fast as you
can and as smart as you can so it's
about prioritizing things and so on and
and still you may not be able to succeed
because in anything that you do
typically many of the variables are out
of your
control let's say you want to win a gold
medal in the next Olympics so there are
certain things in your control how hard
you train your nutrition your diet your
sleep
patterns but there are things you can't
control what kind of facilities can you
afford what kind of coaching can you
afford and even if you really good will
the uh your local Nations your your
nation sport Sports Authorities will
they select you let's say you become
really good but will you be selected for
the Olympics or will there be some some
other Hanky Panky that you can't control
and then let's say you're selected for
the Olympics you go and compete let's
say you're a boxer and you find that the
Olympic boxing Association is
tremendously corrupt then you may do
well but you know the result is not in
your
there are so many things that you cannot
control so ideally you want to have
objectives and and goals
that have parameters and that you can
mostly control and in case you have
things like you can't control then you
know you have to be okay with failure
and even if you can control everything
there is no guarantee of success because
you may not be that good perhaps or you
may be even better who knows you will
not know until you try
and when you try you fail many times so
that's how it is so first of all you
have be really resilient you have to be
smart you have to identify objectives
and tasks that you will genuinely be
able to excel at which means you to
understand yourself and then the
motivation has to come from within you
so that's kind of how we do it everybody
will have a different path a different
way of doing it and uh most people don't
achieve greatness in life understand
that the the people to achieve true
greatness in life are the are the 0.1%
of society or maybe 0.01% of
society most people 95% of people don't
even want to be great they may say that
I want to be great and so on so forth
but they are okay with being average and
there's nothing wrong with that there's
absolutely nothing wrong with wrong with
that not everybody is going to be a
great entrepreneur or a great
industrialist or whatever most people
are happy having a 925 job or 9 to9 job
or whatever it is and getting a good
salary and coming home and so on
so it all depends on so many things but
if you want to be in the top 0.01% you
work really hard there's no holidays
there's no days off and you have need to
be able to understand yourself and do
the things that I kind of laid out so
that's kind of how it goes okay so all
the best and I wish you great
success
okay Sigma says thoughts of
machism
maavi maavi was this
Italian well it's kind it's now part of
Italy so he was this guy who wrote this
book called The Prince Right the prince
I think I heard it once not sure I think
someone stole that book from me you know
that's what people will do never give
anyone your book don't allow anyone to
borrow your book it will disappear it
typically disappears so um he wrote this
book called the prince it's about state
gcraft it's about realism pragmatism and
so on so forth It's about uh how
powerful people can can can gain power
and stain power and that sort of thing
and it is all about a very Cutthroat
view of the world a very realistic
pragmatic amoral view of the world
amoral not immoral but amoral which is
all about the fact that power has
nothing to do with ethics or morality
you either have power or you don't
so uh that's what uh the prince is about
Ma's book and it is kind of a watered
down version of the AR shastra I'm sure
that there is nothing no connection
between the two I'm sure that nikolaki
did not have access to the arastra most
likely overwhelmingly most
likely uh but yeah so you know in the
west they they they kind of term
vishnugupta chanak as the Indian Makia
which is utter
nonsense makali lived in the what the
Middle Ages about I don't remember what
how many years before today maybe about
roughly 500 years before today give or
take and Vishnu chaki lived 2,000 years
before that so about 25
2, roughly 2,500 2,400 years before
today and and the arastra is a much more
detailed document and much more Superior
document compared to uh the prince by
Nicolo makavelli so Mak is is considered
in the west to be the epitomy of real
ISM and pragmatism and statecraft and
being objective and being imoral almost
to the extent of being immoral Etc so
yeah I would say that people should read
the book you may learn a thing or two
from
it um and it's a small book tiny
book Arijit banerji says I got rejected
by a girl whom I liked for a long time
she called me ugly I feel sad yep
happens big deal move on that's what I
would say I know your feelings are hurt
you feel sad and so on so forth but
listen she's not the only girl in the
world okay and if she thinks that you
are whatever that you're not that you're
below a standards why don't you raise
your standards and find a girl who's way
better than
her so the point is the point of the
point in life is that you don't allow
any setback to hamper you for too long
okay she rejected you she said something
nasty to you okay you can sit down for a
day and feel bad next day you move on
she's not the only girl there are better
girls than her out there you know you
can reject somebody without saying
saying nasty things to
someone a guy or a girl can reject
someone without being nasty without
being mean without being
cruel and if she was cruel and mean and
nasty to you maybe she's not a good
person okay so and and if she feels that
she's above you then that's not the kind
of person you want you want to be with
anyway
right uh so the point is don't let it
affect you too much okay what matters in
life is not how pretty or how beautiful
or how handsome or attractive you are
what truly matters in life is what you
achieve in life and you will find that
most of the high Achievers the highest
Achievers the 0.1% of society 0.01% of
society
they typically aren't goodlook or greatl
looking but we have this idea that
they're very attractive because of the
success success is what makes you
attractive so go ahead and succeed in
whatever you're doing
then things will change so the point is
my friend Arijit don't this is no big
deal no big deal okay you have
to you you need to be mentally tough
you will find lots the more rejections
you get in life the better you get at
things
okay so it's no big deal move on from it
there are plenty of other girls I'm sure
better girls than her out there okay all
the
best okay what other questions I'm sure
there are lots of
questions nen says please make another
documentary style video video like the
chingis Khan video uh yeah look there
are very few there is there's kind of a
dir of great topics out there I mean I'm
sure there are hundreds of topics but
the chingis Khan video that I made which
is one of the First videos I made on the
channel is about a mystery that nobody
had soled for about 800 years it's it's
one of the it was it was one of the big
unanswered questions of history that was
quite a topic and it it kind of
was something that was very interested
and yeah so that's why I made that video
and
uh yeah I'm sure I can make more such
videos about interesting
topics uh the only reason I haven't done
that is because it takes a lot of time
to do that not just you have to
structure the video I'll tell you how
the process works okay you have to have
a really interesting topic that lots of
people would be interested in then you
have to have the answer to the big
question then you have to structure the
the video in a specific manner
then you have to record the video I'm
giving you a very brief version of the
process then you have to record the
video maybe a one take two takes
whatever then you have to edit the video
find lots of images find music it's a
long drawn out
process so that's why I've kind of not
not gone down that road again but maybe
maybe I will going forward so thank you
for the suggestion I really appreciate
that
Football news says the US lost more than
12,000 aircrafts helicopters uavs in
Vietnam is the US Military Way weaker
than it seems imagine this they lost I'm
not sure what the number is okay I'm I'm
not aware I don't remember what the
number is how many aircraft Etc they
lost in Vietnam the Americans there were
no uavs those days as far as I know so
you had aircraft of various kinds U
fixed pix wi aircraft like fighter
planes and all and and rotor aircraft
like helicopters so assuming what you
are saying is right okay I'm sure
assuming that they lost more than 12,000
aircraft can you imagine what their
industrial capability was at the time
that they could lose
12,000 plus aircraft and still remain a
superpower it's not way weaker than it
seems it's way more powerful than can
imagine the US
military those days you do not have all
the sophisticated software and
technology and whatever we have today so
those days aircraft also were not that
sophisticated and aircraft were much
cheaper than what what they are today
today the F35 will one F35 will cost
more than hundred
million
one stealth bomber will cost more than a
billion dollars these are incredibly
high value aircraft and they are so high
value because they are so good these are
still the aircraft you can't even see
them on radar you can but you can't kind
of okay I'll don't go into the specifics
the the
details uh in those days aircraft turned
up radar they were pretty cheap and all
so you could afford to lose lots of
aircraft and you would the your industry
would turn out way more so the fact that
they lost so many aircraft and still
remained a superp power and actually
increase the power that tells you how in
incredibly powerful they are so never
underestimate the US military they're
not way weaker than the than the seem
they're way more powerful than you
imagine see it from that perspective
that is the truth you have no idea how
powerful the US military is they can
flatten Nations on
demand okay don't don't ever
underestimate the United
States all right
um let's see some
more questions Malik Sayad says what do
you think of the Law of Attraction and
this sort of pulo science such as
Universe operates on frequencies and
attracts the frequencies imagine the
thing to happen and it happens I I don't
know much about the law of attraction
there's a book by a lady called Ronda
something called The Secret it's about
the law of attraction
and obviously there's no basis of of
whatever that is in in science science
is about observables and and measurables
phenomena quantities objects whatever uh
and obviously there are some things that
you can't really observe like dark
energy but you kind of can measure it
and so on and then there are things like
the Law of Attraction and spirits and
souls and gods and all these are Beyond
science okay science do can does not
deal with these things so it is a I
would say it is incorrect to call this
pseudo science it is not science at all
it's outside of the realm of science
when you say that something is pseudo
scientific it means that it is it claims
to be scientific but it's not the Law of
Attraction doesn't I'm sure it doesn't
claim to be scientific I don't think
these people claim it's
science so I would not call it pseo
scientific I would just call it Beyond
science it is spirituality or or or
whatever but not
science uh and look what's my opinion on
this I have no idea about this okay
that's what I will say uh I have not
seen the law of attraction at work the
Law of Attraction means if you genuinely
desire something really really really
hard and you keep Desiring it
consciously every single day then maybe
that thing will come to you and you will
achieve whatever you
wanted that's kind of what the law of
attraction is but but does it mean that
you should not take any action and just
sit and think think think desire desire
desire I don't think so you have to
desire something with all your heart and
you have to work really hard towards it
and then in that case it may happen in
which case it's not really wrong because
if you really desire something and you
spend all your energy all your time on
that particular objective of
yours then the the chances are pretty
high I would say that you will achieve
what you
want but if you claim that you will
achieve something just by Desiring it
without taking action well that's that's
a joke okay that's kind of hoping to win
the lottery so that's kind of how I see
it uh it is definitely not science I
don't know about frequencies and and
whatnot uh I look at the world from
a from the perspective I'm familiar with
which is the perspective of Science and
physics um and there are lots of
different other perspectives out there
that I'm not familiar with so I don't go
and talk about those if I don't
understand it who am I to criticize that
so that's what I'll say about
that um
okay okay
excited
excited excited says if I like something
whether it's a skill or a subject I have
the urge of learning it after I'm good
at it I lose the interest and yeah
practice it so I can't forget it but is
it
weird
well so if you like something whether
it's a skill like let's say playing
football or a subject like let's say
mathematics I have the urge of learning
it after I'm good at it I lose interest
so if you're good at football you lose
interest in football or if you become
good at math then you lose interest in
math and I practice it so I can't forget
it is it weird well everybody is
different everyone's
different but I'm assuming you're a
student but the thing is once
you come out of your student life and
you are in the world of adults and you
have to have have a livelihood earn a
livelihood Etc then you're going to have
to acquire certain skills in whatever
job you take up and you cannot afford to
lose interest in those things okay and
you're going to be working every day
which means you're going to be utilizing
those skills every single day in which
case you won't have the time to forget
it you may perhaps find over time that
you lose interest but well then if you
want to keep the job and advance in your
career then you can't quite lose
interest so yeah there
are yeah people who are really good at
stuff you know people who acquire skills
very rapidly they kind of tend to lose
interest in things once they have
mastered it so one has to be careful as
to not be like this when you have a job
and you have a career so I don't think
it's weird it depends on your
personality it depends on your aptitude
at various things and so
on all
right Mr Osama Trump says is a nuclear
armed Iran a threat to India you think
isra and the US will use India to tackle
Iran if Iran becomes nuclear armed let's
go to the
map so Iran is next next door to India
we have a temporary nation in between
but then you have Iran and Iran and
India have historically have reasonably
good relations baring a few setbacks
here and there now we have a nuclear
armed Pakistan which is a terrorist
Nation India is a nuclear power very
responsible one then Israel is a is an
Undeclared nuclear power and and Iran
may be on the verge of becoming a
nuclear power they have had this nuclear
program for quite some time and I
suspect that they may already have
sufficient file material to maybe build
a few Warheads maybe five or a handful
so the question is if Iran becomes a
nuclear power is that a threat to India
my perspective is
that India need not be worried about a
nuclear powered
Iran of course if Iran acquires 500
nuclear warheads or th000 then that kind
of exerts pressure on the entire
neighborhood on the entire uh West Asia
region and or even the subcontinent but
as long as Iran has 5 10 20 nuclear
warheads
Iran won't really be a threat to
definitely not
India so how does a nation become a
threat to someone a a nation becomes a
threat to its neighbors it if it becomes
overwhelming inly no more
powerful than all its neighbors then
it's a threat to everybody it may have
good intentions but it has the capacity
to steamroll you now India I don't know
how many nuclear warheads we have the
West says we have roughly 130 nuclear
warheads it's known that India has
sufficient file material for about 2
3,000 Warheads actually but let's say
India has 13 warheads and Iran Iran
acquires let's say 10 or 20 Warheads is
Iran a threat to India not really what
if Iran acquires 300 nuclear warheads
then even though India and Iran don't
have any unfriendly
relations you could perceive that as a
threat okay
so that's how it goes even a friend of
yours even the most friendly Nation if
they suddenly acquire or over time
acquire three times the nuclear weapons
that you have
the relationship changes let me give you
a very rough very very very crude
example okay let's say you have a cat at
home very nice cat very cute cat very
friendly cat right now let's say and
that's how big is a cat typically about
this big you big yeah now let's say I
magically transform that cat into
something into the same animal but three
times the size
okay three times the size of a house cat
by
Magic so now your cat is the size of a
leopard you think your cat will behave
in the same way with you now that it's a
leopard sized cat I assure you it won't
Its Behavior will
change the size makes a
difference the size of its claws and its
teeth makes a difference so the same
entity if it is transformed into
something else
will behave differently VAV you and
everybody else so a nuclear powered Iran
nuclear armed Iran is not really threat
for India if it has 5 10 20 Warheads 50
50 would be kind of
concerning so you have to look at these
factors first of all do we have a
hostile relationship with this nation we
don't have a hostile relationship with
Iran no we don't do we have any disputes
with this nation border disputes or
whatever we don't we don't have a border
dispute or any such thing with Iran does
Iran do something that imp that that
infringes on India's national interests
does India do anything that infringes on
Iran's national interest not really so
overall the relationship with between
the two Nations is reasonably good it
can certainly be better but it's
reasonably good that's a good start now
if Iran becomes a nuclear
power as long as it's not too many
nuclear weapons 5 10 20 it's no big deal
for India it's actually a concern for
Pakistan now so that's the deal now do
you think Israel and us will use India
to tackle Iran that's up to us do we
want to be used as a Pawn on somebody's
geopolitical chessboard or do we want to
have our own foreign policy independent
of others if we want to have our own
foreign policy that's independent of
others and we in such a way that we
cannot be used by others we have to be
sufficiently powerful in our own
right which means that we need to become
much more powerful than we are right now
right now see our neighborhood the
Americans can do whatever they want they
can do a regime change operation right
next door to us they can well you have a
civil war in Burma right next to us we
are unable to control our own
neighborhood and there's so much
interference in India's Internal Affairs
right now from the Americans quite
visible so India will have to become
more
powerful but even as things stand I
don't think the US can use India to
tackle other nations
uh for example they would like to use
India to to be a counterweight against
China and to do various things against
China I don't think we are willing to
act as a pawn and the same would go with
Iran
okay Jen says the re this recent news
that Pakistan is going to supply a large
amount massive amounts of arms and
ammunition to Bangladesh do such activ
is threatened India's chicken neck area
in the
future may the chicken neck area
increase in size okay where's the
chicken neck area it's a Siliguri
Corridor I'm sure we are all familiar
with
it this area is the chicken neck
area Siliguri bdog Etc that that area
and it's about 25 30 kilm wide how wide
is it let's see roughly 24 23 22 km wide
so it's it's a point of concern it's an
area of concern
uh and the theory is that if if somebody
wants to cut off the Far East of India
from the rest of India they have to take
the they have to take over the chicken
neck area the Siliguri
Corridor now yes I've heard this news
that Pakistan is going to supply a large
quantity of arms ammunition Etc to
Bangladesh I am not surprised in the
least why is
that Pakistan since 2022 February or or
when when was the Imran Khan coup in
which he was outed whenever it was
sometime in the first half of 2022 since
that time Pakistan has firly become a us
wasal a us wasal a US C State a US
puppet state so
Pakistan is a us vasal and now
Bangladesh since the events of the coup
regime change operation that happened
recently Bangladesh is also a us wasal
so one wasal to another they will do
whatever is in the best interest of each
other and obviously these decisions are
not taken by the government of Pakistan
or the Pakistani army these are
instructions given to them from higher
up from their
masters which is
well the United States who else right so
there is going to be
increasing Synergy between pakist
between West Pakistan and East Pakistan
okay they would like to recreate a
scenario where you have where India is
is surrounded India is planked on two
sides by East Pakistan and West Pakistan
there's going to be a growing amount of
synergy between the two Nations there's
going to be a growing amount of
coordination and synchronization between
the two Nations that is definitely a
point of concern for
India um and such activities May indeed
threaten the Indian chicken neck area
the Siliguri Corridor area very much
India is going to be have to be extra
careful super
careful uh
so there we are in the future will will
the Chien neck increase in size well it
depends on various factors but it may
increase in size I would say that we
need to create a buffer state within
Bangladesh okay so if you look at
Bangladesh there are these areas to the
west of Bangladesh rangapur rajshahi Etc
we need to
uh probably um encourage the Bangladesh
Bangladeshi Hindus to create a buffer
State a separate nation in this region a
nation only for
Hindus in which case we will have a
reasonable amount of buffer and you can
say that the chicken neck has de facto
increased in size so yeah that's what I
would say it's all speculation right now
but India cannot afford to always remain
on the back foot if the border with
Bangladesh with East Pakistan is a
poorest border as we know very well then
please understand a poorest border works
both ways you you've had this influx of
Bangladesh is illegal Bangladeshi
infiltration into India for decades well
it can work the other way too if it's a
poor as border so let's kind of use that
to our advantage that's what I would
say
um anol Kumar says should India host the
Olympics in 2036 I'm asking this
question because most of the political
analysts and YouTubers are saying it
will be a disaster to host the Olympics
in India you know there are certain very
powerful Nations that
have of of of in recent times had this
policy
of
promoting certain influencers YouTubers
political analysts within India certain
very powerful Nations have this policy
and they're quite open and blatant about
this policy they promote certain
YouTubers they promote certain so-called
influencers and they play this
this game of subnational
diplomacy and they
promote and and
and promote in various ways allegedly
certain
alleged political parties in India
allegedly okay it is said it is said
that's what one hears on the Grape Wine
so with that said why are we surprised
if some YouTubers and influencers and
analysts Etc are claiming
the Olympics if we host the Olympics in
2036 it'll be disaster for India why are
we surprised about it my my other
question is why can't we have our own
opinion if so and so influencer or
analyst or YouTuber has said that do we
have to take them
seriously we should have the
ability to critically analyze things
ourselves most people I see they listen
to the opinions of certain analysts and
influencers and YouTubers they
like and that's what they believe
whatever these people say why can't you
analyze things yourself can't you look
at information yourself you need to
develop the ability the skills to do
that that's what I keep urging
everybody so I
disagree that hosting the Olympics in
2036 will be a disaster for India why
will it be a disaster some YouTubers I
am aware are are spreading this this
narrative
that hosting the Olympics will be a
disaster for India and I'll assure you
about something you you know YouTubers
influencers analysts are categorized
right right-wing versus left
wing in case you're not aware some of
the so-called X-Wing or y- wiers are
actually on the other side but you're
not aware of it they're playing a double
game that also you should be aware of
whether it's this side or that side this
Wing or that wing
there's always the possibility somebody
who's on this Wing or that Wing may
actually be batting for the other side
please understand this okay I'm not
naming
anybody and I'm not calling out anyone
I'm just saying in general be aware of
these things I'm of the opinion that we
should host the
Olympics of course we should do it in in
the right way in a sustainable way so if
you create all this infrastructure let's
say you create like 5 10 sports
facilities stadiums whatever
you should ensure that after the
Olympics are over you're going to keep
on using them and these are going to
promote Sports in India for a long time
so recently we had the the football
World Cup in which our Gulf nation which
one Qatar was
it um now I'm I'm I believe most of that
sporting infrastructure stadium is lying
unused so that sort of the sort of
scenario is bad you invest hundreds of
millions of dollar billions of dollars
in creating all this infrastructure you
only use it once for the world cup or
the Olympics and then you never use it
again that should not happen so it
should be something that is properly
planned and
executed so as long as we do that I
think we should be fine it should be it
would be great for India so I am of the
opinion that we should certainly host
the Olympics in 2036 of course we would
win bid but let's
see okay
Mr Osama Trump says Russia has given a
statement that the war will now not be
limited to up to Ukraine but will go on
the internet Europe as well especially
France do you think Russia and Iran will
jointly initiate World War II I don't
want World War II I don't think any
World War I is going to happen anytime
soon I want I wish it I hope it never
happens look
statements I can give a thousand
statements anybody can say whatever they
wants please understand the incredibly
large difference between words and
actions you know politicians most
politicians I think all
politicians uh we know they make lots of
statements now do they and lots they
make lots of promises especially during
campaigning for elections do they keep
all their
promises obviously
not I cannot think of a single
politician who keeps all of his or her
election promises I can't think of a
single person can't think of a single
one so considering that with that in
mind Please be aware that geopolitics
also that kind of game there's a lot of
mental
games that that go on lot of mental dis
disintegration strategies are employed
by putting out statements by making
strong statements and sometimes
obfuscating things sometimes
misdirection is is involved and so much
more so look I don't care what
statements are given
generally in war you know like like the
great like what's his name sunzu right
the the Chinese guy one of the most
famous statements attributed to sunzu is
that all Warfare is about
deception so if you're planning to do
something do you think it makes sense to
Telegraph that in advance that hey I'm
going to do these things now in the war
that we are fighting against each other
I'm going to do this in the next coming
two three weeks or two three months do
you think it makes sense to do that to
tell your opponent in advance what your
strategy is going to be like no makes no
sense so statements I don't care about
statements I only look at what are the
actions that are being
taken
and it
makes sense that the war is not limited
to one
domain war is a multi-domain thing
multi-dimensional thing there is
propaganda War
there is cyber War we don't know what
cyber attacks are happening right
now okay even the recipient of of a
Cyber attack will keep quiet about that
often so as to not let the opponent know
that they've
succeeded uh so Warfare exists at so
many different levels there is lawfare
there is propaganda Warfare there is
social media
Warfare uh there is diplomatic Warfare
and India is the recipient of some of
this Warfare right now from our
so-called friends so so that's the
situation the war obviously is not
confined to just the the the physical
domain of Ukraine and that's something
that's already been going on for quite
some time it is beyond
Ukraine sanctions are War sanctions you
know what sanctions are economic
sanctions it's Siege Warfare it is the
modern equivalent of Siege Warfare you
besiege a nation or a city in in the old
days you would have Siege Warfare which
means you have a city that has walls you
know defensive walls fortifications and
the enemy will come and take over the
entire land around the city they can't
break into the city because of the walls
but they will starve the city of all
materials all resources so no more food
can reach the city if the city has a
source of water great otherwise you
can't even get water and then you will
starve them out and wait them to surren
wait for them to surrender that's Siege
Warfare today you have economic
sanctions that do exactly the same thing
you starve a nation of of its
requirements of of the resources that it
needs you wait for them to crumble so
that is Warfare the Americans are doing
that against Russia that goes beyond
Ukraine all so many other nations are
involved in that so there are so many
domains to war okay so we should not be
surprised about that but the Russians
will never tell anyone in advance what
they're going to do statements well
statements have their own place in the
thing but understand it it's much more
than that
Mna
wosu says you said that the US is
trying all its ways to hinder the growth
of India I'm not saying it's trying all
its
ways I'm not saying it is trying
everything in its power to hinder the
growth of India if the Americans try
everything in their power to hinder the
growth of India they will impose
economic sanctions on India the same
kind of sanctions they impos on Russia
have they done that they have not so how
can you say that they are trying
always
no what does the US want from India the
the US wants India to remain at around
$4 trillion or5 trillion dollar as as
economy you know they want India to
remain a four or five trillion dollar
economy not rise beyond that and if
India's economy grows the economic
growth should be slow
India should remain a middle power India
should keep on aspiring forever to be a
great power but never become a great
power economically or
otherwise so they will take specific
calibrated actions to to achieve this
objective but they won't impose
sanctions on India unless we do certain
things so I have never ever said that
the US is trying always every single way
possible to hinder the growth of India
please understand there are nuances in
geopolitics it's not black and white
there are lots of Shades of
Gray so I don't know what the Sosa
agreement is they've signed all kinds of
agreements with
India there's a lot of cooperation
happening between the US and
India so they will cooperate with India
as well as hinder India they will
cooperate in with India wherever it
suits them and it benefits them they
will hinder the growth of India in a lot
of other ways so they don't want India
to become the next
China so that is a situation please
understand geopolitics is nuanced and
please don't attribute things to me that
I have not said I have never said that
the US is trying every way or always to
hinder India's
growth
okay AR says presidential republic
versus parliamentary Republic
presidential way better especially for
India the larger a nation is see the
principle behind this is that is very
simple the larger a nation is the more
centralized its rule has to be if you
decentralize the
rule in a very large Nation you're going
to end up with multiple Nations it's
going to
fragment when it comes to a very small
nation let's say like Singapore you can
decentralize everything
because it's anywhere
centralized okay the smaller a nation
the more you can afford to
decentralize and the larger a nation the
more centralized the power has to be
look at the US it has a presidential
system makes sense for them to have a
presidential system they have a
two-party system which is just one step
above one party State like China or
North Korea so they talk about democracy
but they are implementing what's best
for them which is not very democratic
now we in India have
copied the governance
system of a small
island in the Atlantic
Ocean of of a nation that is part of a
small that is on a small island and not
fully but partially on the small island
so it is what that's
England or the UK okay and we have
copied their Parliament their governance
system which is Westminster democracy
that system evolved over
[Music]
roughly several
centuries in this very small part of the
world and it is well suited for that
part of the world it had a monarchy it
still has a monarchy do we have a
monarchy no so we have copied A
system that is eminently
unsuitable for a subcontinent sized
Nation like
ours we should have adopted A system
that is best suited for us and
historically we have had very different
systems before we got colonized invaded
conquered and colonized so I am very
clear that the presidential system
system is far better for India than the
parliamentary system far better and
because we copied this system of the
UK we had to make certain silly changes
to it
see in the UK you have a you have a
House of Lords Right In The House of the
commons House of Commons of House of
Lords so we we have done away with our
princely states and we don't have any
Lords so we had to create this rajas SAA
because we have to blindly slavishly
copy the British right so we had to
create this rajas SAA with with this
artificially artificial structure and
today you have a situation where the
rajas SAA kind of has a v or the L saaba
in the UK you don't have
that in the UK the house of L Lords
cannot veto
anything that the House of Commons
does they can make recommendations and
so on but they cannot veto any any bill
that is passed any law that is passed or
any decision that is taken in the in the
House of Commons in India the rajas SAA
can veto things which is horrible for
democracy because it is the L SAA that
is the directly elected representatives
of the people
the rajas saaba is indirectly indirect
representation and lots of that is not
really Democratic at all so that is one
problem secondly the the head of state
in the UK is the king or the queen so
because we don't have that in India we
had to create this this ceremonial
position of the president of
India there should be no ceremonial
positions there should only be actual
positions of power so we have done all
these weird things I don't think it's
it's suitable for our nation I think we
should have a more direct kind of
democracy presidential democracy where
people are allowed to choose and vote
for the president the the person who
will lead the nation for the next X
amount of years four five whatever you
can't even vote for your prime minister
today you can only vote for your local
MP and then the MPS get together and
decide who will be the Prime Minister
and that that's problematic so we need a
better system for sure for sure
man panchal says I'm 28 years old I was
lost in terms of career due to some bad
decisions I took and due to mental
health issues is it too late now too
late to revive my career now 28 you're
young
bro absolutely not too
late it's never too late to start
something
new uh so listen so whatever happened in
the past happened you got you don't
forget it okay you canot forget what
happened in the past it should serve as
a reference point for you or a set of
reference points for you that these
things went wrong for so and so reasons
and that's for you to decide why it went
wrong that's for you to understand and
that is obviously something that adds to
your experience and to your
understanding of the world and of
yourself and if you're 28 it's
absolutely not too late to revive your
career look life is long to today with
the kind of advances in science
technology Healthcare we have that we
have you can be a fully functional human
being with with as long as you make good
choices and good life live a good
lifestyle you can be a fully functional
functional human being all the way into
your 80s so I think you're just starting
off in life right now you know what they
say is that life starts right life
really begins at the age of 40 because
until then you're you're Le you're
learning stuff which is kind of
true and uh so I I would absolutely
disagree that it's too late to revive
your career or or to make a different
career choice now there's a lot that you
can
do as long as you do it well you're
smart about it and you work hard
absolutely all the options I would say
are open for you the longer you wait in
life to make changes the fewer options
you have so if you're 28 and you want to
make a change in your career or revive
your career year you will have a certain
number of options if you wait till 38
the options will reduce if you wait till
48 you will have even fewer options
unless you can totally re reinvent
yourself so I think 28 is not too old
it's absolutely not too late as long as
you are positive and and you work really
hard and you understand your strengths
and and weaknesses and play accordingly
so I would say go for it absolutely go
for it and all the best sir all the best
udit Mahesh says could another
Insurgency occur in the Northeast under
the current current government with the
misos and cookies join hands since they
share the same
ethnicity well
I after after the recent developments in
Bangladesh and given the situation in
Burma the Civil War that's going on
right now it's India will have to be
really really really careful about the
Northeast the Far East of
India one I can assure you that we will
have to be really watchful when it comes
to Bangladesh it is very possible almost
almost a
guarantee that you will see the same
kind of problematic behavior from East
Pakistan or Bangladesh that we used to
see in the 70s ' 80s ' 90s 2000s from
Pakistan West Pakistan we're going to
have to be really careful they will they
will nurture and promote all kinds of
anti-india elements which means
separatist elements and so
on from Bangladeshi territory it is very
likely to
happen which means that you could have
such problems in the
Northeast right so yeah I agree with you
it could happen and India India is going
to have is going to have its hands full
we really really need to focus on the
northeast we need to fortify our
defenses and our capabilities there
military
capabilities
uh civilian defense capabilities all of
that we need to do
that um yeah so it will need to happen
I'm sure the government of India is is
doing whatever is required about the
Miso and cookies I think the less we
speak about the Miso and cookies the
better but uh I get your point then you
are not far from the
truth
right okay vishak ner says if a country
could surpass the superpower United
States how would the country do it and
resist their
bullying well that's that's the that's
the whole thing
right it's very difficult to surpass a
superpower that is at the peak of its
strength right now the US is at the peak
of its military strength people talk
about the U us as being a nation and
Decline and so on so forth there is
decline happening in the US it is
societal decline the fabric of society
in the US there there's Strife in
society there are increasing racial
tensions Society is being destabilized
by the massive influx of illegal
immigrants happening the southern Border
in the US that the current government
the current regime is engineering that
is that happening uh there is a lack
there is a complete collapse of the
family system everybody is a single
mother or single father every child
comes from a family that's broken
divorced
family the economy isn't doing great
there is tremendous inflation everything
is becoming more expensive that sort of
decline is very visible in the US
societal decline but as a military power
the US has never been stronger than what
it is today please understand that H
with that understood how could a
nation How could a nation uh surpass the
US first of
all it won't happen overnight it'll take
50 years let's let's talk about let's
let's be open we're talking about India
aren't
we obviously we're talking about India
here look India cannot even dream of
surpassing the US for another 50 years
unless something precipitous happens in
the US and they they completely collapse
which would send send the whole world
into chaos and then then all bets are
off but if the US remains superpower the
way it is for the next 50 years they
will do their best to prevent Any Nation
like India from rising to a great power
status or a super power status and super
power means you have complete control or
significant control over the entire
world's Economy Supply chains trade
routes all of that which which means you
have a gigantic array of extr
territorial Global military bases all
that the US
has so um so how could India do such a
thing by slowly growing and being very
quiet about
it Indians have this tendency to shout
and scream from the rooftops we are a
superpower we are this no keep quiet
like ding shoing said hide your strength
and bide your time keep a low profile
that's what India needs to do so we need
to stop dis discussing the superpower
thing we are not a superpower we are not
going to be a superpower for the next 50
years unless something very drastic
happens um what we can Aspire see we
have to take it day by day step by step
we are right now A4 trillion dollar
economy I think we we have now become a
four trillion dollar economy the US is
what 20 plus right China is 1718
trillion doll and then comes India and
and then there's Germany and Japan which
will soon uh become history because
India will surpass them soon that's a
guarantee so India has to do it slowly
steadily day by day week by week month
by month year by year take it a day at a
time and stop acting bigger than what
you are keep a low profile work hard
that's all IND needs to
do uh and resisted bullying well how do
you resist a superpowers bullying by
having other powerful friends and by
having lots of alliances multi-alignment
multi- allying and all that so if India
the best way the ideal way for India to
resist American
bullying would be to have great
relations with not just Russia but also
China well
China that's that's that's
farfetched considering the past history
of China VAV
India so I don't have the solutions but
if India can do that have great
relations with Russia as well as with
China if we can engineer that then we
will be much more difficult to
bully so lots of ifs and buts here but
yeah the the As a matter of principle
you have to do it quietly you have to
hide your strength and buy your time be
very patient work as hard as possible
and have as many powerful friends as
possible and don't step on the
superpowers toes as far as possible
keep them happy that's how you do it and
you do it for the next 50 years then you
will become hopefully superpower that is
how you do it
sir okay love
yapping says in your opinion what has
held back India's potential the most
historical atrocities like famines or
the past governments' ability to address
corruption and other ongoing issues look
what has held back India's potential the
most right look these historical
atrocities like the
genocide perpetrated by the Turks the
genocide perpetrated by the British the
famines and all of that that is in the
past that is in the past tense it
happened and it's over now there is no
genocide happening today there is no
famine being engineered by foreign
powers
today right and if you look at 1947
onwards then no such thing was happening
so then what's a what has held back
India's potential the most first of
alluvian
socialism India in 1947 was far ahead
than most Asian economies China was in a
shambles Civil War in China Japan was on
its knees or or even further down they
had been nuked two nuclear tests on
Japanese people on Japanese civilians
and the whole country is destroyed
that's what Japan was South Korea was
Korea at the time was an extremely poor
country and the Korean war was going to
happen
50s so if you look at the whole of Asia
India was in a great
position we had our entire
infrastructure intact we had a very
powerful military we had the most
powerful military in
Asia the British Indian army which
became the Indian Army and Navy in our
Force we had the most powerful military
in Asia and and
yet we continueed to wallow in
mediocrity Japan took off China after
the '90s took off because they made a
choice in the 70s and
80s if we had opened up our economy and
done so
judiciously in 1947 and if we had
adopted the right
policies then we would have taken off in
the 40s 50s itself
and then it would have been impossible
for China to surpass India or catch up
with India so what held back India's
potential was the policies of the post
1947 governments of India the economic
policies mainly and of course the system
the system that was created by the
British and continued by the Indian
governments post 1947 the entire system
the governance system various government
governance organs various institutions
were all created by the
British and they were created by the
British
to to help them rule over India and
extract everything of value out of India
and keep the common man woman and child
of India under the heavy boot of the
Govern governance
Machinery that's what the British
created the these institutions for and
the institutions were never really
reformed and they still continue in the
same way since
to rule over
India and to rule over Indians so the
the Masters have changed but the system
has remained the same and it operates in
the same way as it used to operate
before
47 and there's a there's allegedly a
tremendous amount of corruption at
various levels in the governance
Machinery
allegedly I'm sure everybody has
experien this
allegedly so that's what has held back
India
imagine there's no corruption in India
today or 90% of the corruption is is
dealt with India will take off India
will take off imagine how much inertia
there is in India because of these
issues imagine how much of the money of
the common man woman and child of India
is being wasted on G in giving bribes
how much time is being wasted fighting
the
system so these are the things that that
are holding back India right now the
education system is another great
example of this horror it's a
continuation of the 19th century
colonial British education system and
what does it do it produces graduates
who have no skills and then if those
graduates get jobs Whoever has given
them the job needs to train them from
scratch and so on so there are so all
these issues systemic issues and
allegedly tremendous amounts of
corruption in various parts of the
governance Machinery allegedly these are
the things that are holding back India's
potential even today and have done so
since
okay xus Yus zus says one dimensional is
space
xaxis
2D is space y axis plus xaxis 3D is XYZ
axis 3 axis right okay 4D is all that
plus the
time so why is 4D time parameter instead
of space time parameter can exist in 1D
also please explain you can take X as a
Time Dimension time coordinate if you
wish and don't consider the other three
spatial coordinates if you wish it's
entirely up to
you so there are four dimensions that we
are aware of
length breadth height and time so you
don't have to start with the x axis as
the as as one spatial Dimension you can
start with the x-axis and and consider
it to be the dimension of time it's
entirely arbitrary instead of calling it
the x-axis you can call it the P axis if
you wish or the T Axis or the Q Axis or
the m a it's entirely up to you these
are all arbitrary
notations but there are four dimensions
that we are aware of and one dimension
we are aware of very only vaguely which
is the time Dimension but that's how we
were able to that's how alberon was able
to construct theory of general
relativity which is one of the most
successful theories of in in science
that we
have so yes you are right time as a
parameter can be considered to be
considered can be considered
independently of the other Dimensions if
you wish if it it if it uh helps you in
your calculations or if you desire to do
so there is no one stopping you from
doing it there's no one stopping any
physicist from constructing an access
with time as a dimension and ignoring
the other three spatial Dimensions if
you so desire but what do you get out of
it is the question
right so each of these dimensions you
can consider them independently of the
other if you so wish but to solve
problems in physics and to get actual
real world
results you have to
consider
Dimensions not independent of each other
but together generally neonian physics
you have three
dimensions you can you can start with
one dimension only but then you you have
to introduce time which is the T
parameter in your
Newtonian uh equations of motion and all
that so that's that's why you have to
start considering the dimensions
together because otherwise you don't get
any real world
results why am I always clean shaven I
don't know maybe because if I don't
shave then I will look like I don't know
Taliban maybe long hair and beard good
God I'm I'm 61 so once again I think
it'll scare people if I have a beard so
I and and I like the clean shaven look
any anyway I I think it was once during
University that I didn't shave for a
month and I had a beard only once after
that I uh ensure that I was always
reasonably clean
shaven book recommendations for linear
algebra and real
analysis linear algebra how come I have
a book right here cuep Singh is a great
book if you want to start off with okay
really really well written book Kul
Singh uh on linear algebra and if you
want a book on really real
analysis what a
coincidence Kul Singh once again num
this is not really real analysis this is
number Theory but it's it's a great book
number for number Theory real
analysis um where do you go you go with
Rudin baby Rudin big
Rudin uh can't think of a recommendation
off the top of my head I think you could
go with
um what's his name uh what was the child
prodigy mathematician who is no longer a
child Fields Medal
winner uh Terrence tow I think Terren T
has written a couple of really good
books on analysis real analysis or oral
analysis
so there's there's plenty of options
available but definitely for linear
algebra you would you should go with
with the cuep Singh and obviously Strang
Gilbert Strang Gilbert Strang has really
good books on linear algebra at least a
couple of books and if you want to solve
problems and and get good at the subject
by solving lots of problems go for the
Sha series books a whole bunch of those
over here back back from my my college
and university days
Grim soad says is mathematics the
programming language of the universe yes
if there was a programmer who coded the
universe then the language he or she or
it used was clearly mathematics because
mathematics is
is what
underlies the patterns and regularities
that we observe in the universe it's all
mathematical which means that the
programmer who coded the
universe used mathema matics is the
language or maybe whatever language they
used we perceive those patterns and
regularities as the laws of
mathematics isn't
it
uh Vikram geopolitical says if you have
to live under the rule of either lenen
or M dong whom would you choose I would
rather choose to escape via Wormhole to
a different Universe because good God
disaster from both both
sides no way H imagine having that
choice it's no choice really
terrible
okay winter Ragnar wolf says if India
hadn't been colonized see this is a
completely hypothetical question all
speculation you can answer anything it
it may be true if India hadn't been
colonized what level of cultural
technological and economic advancement
do you think the country would have
achieved today maybe we would have
advanced tremendously in all spheres
culturally technologically economically
or maybe we would have done modest
progress there is no way of knowing
because it's entirely hypothetical and
speculative isn't
it um but yes India would have been
definitely better off than than what it
is today that I can assure you we would
have an indigenous education system and
an indigenous form of
governance uh we we would never have
been de industrialized you know the
British de-industrialized India so all
those things wouldn't have happened we
would have better genetics because our
best people most of the people who
represented our best genetics they were
the Warriors and and the leaders who
were all killed off so a lot India would
have been a much
better uh civilization than what it is
today we would have higher standards for
sure right now we are wowing in
mediocrity
we would have much higher standards than
what we have today we would have much
much better leaders than what we have
today so overall India would have been
much better but culturally culturally
also India would have been so much more
better today we wouldn't be speaking a
foreign language we
wouldn't uh our entertainment system
would would be much
better our our regional local languages
indigenous languages would not be dying
like they today e ically we would have
been much better so overall I would say
we would overall would have been much
better than where we are today but to
what extent to what degree that's hard
to tell because n number of things can
happen Shri ramachandra namah says how
does the Earth's magnetic field protect
itself from solar flares uh the magnetic
field doesn't protect itself from solar
flar it protects the Earth from the
solar wind what is the solar
wind oh where do you have it there you
have it wow I don't know you could do
that can I see
Mars you can even see Mars uh
Venus you can even see Venus from here
anyway let's come back to that I
apologize I I like
toys give me a toy I'll play with it
okay so what here's the deal the Earth
has a magnetic field okay what is the
origin of the magnetic field the origin
of the magnetic field is the interior of
the Earth this liquid metal below the
magma magma layer which is which which
is in in motion and you have charged
particles in it and charged particles in
motion give rise to uh a magnetic field
which all of which well it it originates
in special
relativity so we have a magnetic field a
reasonably powerful magnetic field the
lines of force they kind of origin at
the poles roughly around the poles North
Pole South
Pole now you have something called the
solar wind the solar wind is this stream
of charged particles protons electrons
Etc that flow out of the sun tremendous
amount of solar wind is Flowing out of
the Sun at every at any given point in
time it's
plasma so and then you also have Cosmic
resin much more okay that that comes
from all over the the
Galaxy so but we are talking about solar
wind here not solar flares solar wind
and solar flares also give off large
quantities of solar wind charged
particles that can mess up the
electronics on the planet and
inundate the surface of the planet with
all kinds of
terrifying particles which can give you
cancer destroy your DNA mutate your DNA
cause damage of orines and all that so
what happens is that when you have a
magnetic
field charged particles they
move in curved lines in magnetic
fields okay now the what that does is
that we have these magnetic lines of
force coming out of the of the of the
pole polar region of the earth and these
magnetic lines of force they trap the
charged particles coming from the Sun
and concent them in some parts of the
Earth where they enter the atmosphere
and glow and that's what causes the
auroras and most of the these charged
particles they they are trapped in the
magnetic field and they never really
reach the atmosphere and the surface of
the Earth so essentially that's kind of
what
happens and the magnetic field of the
earth is what has what
essentially ensures that we have this
kind of life on the planet and that's
why we still have oceans on the
planet if you look at Mars it's very
clear looking at the surface of the
planet of Mars of the planet Mars that
there were once oceans on Mars oceans of
water there were rivers on Mars you can
see rivers and canyons and all the
shapes left behind by that but where is
the water all the surface water has
disappeared except for wherever you have
some
ice so why did all the water disappear
it's because Mars lost its magnetic
field so the solar wind Stripped Away
the atmosphere until we have a very thin
atmosphere left on Mars and the solar
wind all the charged particles they
destroyed the water also they ionized
the
water in in the process of very slow
electrolysis so water was ionized
dissociated into hydrogen and oxygen and
all the water disappeared from the plan
surface of the planet so that's what
would happen if we did not have a
magnetic field on the planet the
magnetic field traps the solar wind and
prevents it from
destroying the atmosphere and
water
okay ishan Gupta says how do you think
the present day India would have been if
Turks had never invaded clearly much
better much
better Amit Tria says what's your view
on the recent F16 crash Amit I'm sure is
referring to the incident in Ukraine the
Americans have dispatched a number of
F-16 fighter planes you know it's a
50-year old fighter plane which is still
origa quite good and they have
dispatched number of these fighter
planes to Ukraine and the ukrainians
will use them against
Russia and one what one hears apparently
is that apparently the F-16 that that
crashed was shot down by Ukraine itself
in a case of friendly fire you know
sometimes you have these incidents
unfortunate incidents in which you in
which your
defense
mechanism um it shoots down your your
own aircraft it's known to happen at
times okay so it looks like that's what
happened the Ukrainian air defenses shut
down then their own aircraft essentially
that's what I hear not 100% confirmed or
sure but that's what I've heard so
that's what I can tell you
da says the future of Bangladesh
according to you and its impacts on
India well first of all let me start by
saying that I wish the people of
Bangladesh nothing but happiness and and
prosperity
okay
uh may they get everything they desire
in life and may no Misfortune Beall them
let let me preface by saying that now
the truth is Bangladesh was artificially
cowed out of India in 1947 as East
Pakistan and then in 71 it it
transformed itself into a different
Nation Bangladesh and the influence of
the Pakistani army was was removed by
the Indian Armed Forces India liberated
Bangladesh from
Pakistan uh so that's what happened but
the truth is Bangladesh is still an
artificial
Nation it's been artificially created
carved out of India so I think
eventually long-term 100-year Horizon
probably this entire region will revert
to becoming Indian again maybe 100 years
maybe 200 years from now you will need
some cultural changes civilizational
changes to happen before we
can reincorporate Bangladesh into India
until then it will exist in some shape
or
form um as long as the as the US is all
powerful in the world they will be a
US vasal state like they are right now
and the people of Bangladesh are already
beginning to realize that the school has
not really empowered the students the
school that happened
recently in which Sheik was
outed it has been portrayed as a student
Revolution as a student coup as as
as as a restoration of democracy and
whatnot so if it was really a student
Revolution or whatever they call it why
is not a single student leader a member
of the cabinet in the government in this
new government
why it's becoming apparent and clear
that the students were used as a
pretext to achieve a geopolitical aim
objective outcome in in Bangladesh and
now we hear that there are new round
there's a new round of students student
protest that's happening against this
girl this new regime that has been put
in place
undemocratically so I think there's
going to be a period of turmoil in
Bangladesh maybe a long period of
turmoil when the people slowly start
realizing that they have been
played that this new regime is nothing
but a puppet of a foreign country just
like what you have in
Pakistan so I think there's going to be
a period of turmoil I see that their
economy slowing
down uh I don't have a tremendous amount
of Hope for the adesh economy it was
doing well as long as shik Kaz was in
power now it's going to flounder in the
coming
years
unfortunately so if the people of
Bangladesh are not careful if the new
regime is not careful Bangladesh could
very well go down the same road that
Pakistan has gone
down that's what could happen that's
what will most likely happen
look Pakistan in Pakistan the people
have people of Pakistan have no say in
the governance of their nation and the
future of their Nation there's nothing
the people of Pakistan can do in about
about it because the nation is
controlled by the
military in Bangladesh also the nation
will most likely be controlled by the
military the military is the backbone of
the nation in Pakistan it owns the
nation in
Pakistan sooner or later the same thing
will happen in Bangladesh you will have
a puppet prime minister
who will have no real power and the real
power will be in the armed
forces and they will over time run the
show in Bangladesh any way they want as
long as they fulfill the objectives of
the
superpower that is what I see happening
in the short to medium term at least
medium term in
Bangladesh and for the situation to
improve India will have to rise which
will take 20 30 years so for the next 20
30 years things are not going to look
good for
Bangladesh Bangladesh is going to is
going to go backwards it's going to
become East Pakistan again that's how I
see things going in Bangladesh I hope
I'm wrong I have nothing against the
people of Bangladesh I wish them well
but that but their fate is no longer in
their hands they believe they've
achieved some great success wait and
watch come back and watch this video in
years and you will see that I was right
okay ambati says Will trump be able to
revive the US economy and stop the war
in Ukraine right after he becomes
elected as a president of the US in case
that
happens
look um there must be some things he can
do which can reasonably rapidly
change the
economic situation in the US I'm sure
some things will take much
longer when it comes to the war the
Ukraine war he can stop it in one day if
he wants by giving Putin whatever Putin
wants what does Putin want what are
Putin's
objectives in Ukraine first regime
change in Kev zinski gone a pro Russia
government comes to power in Kev that's
number one number two to
all um denazification of Ukraine means
all these
Nazi you know Nazi
elements should be let's say neutralized
in
Ukraine and third no more NATO influence
in Ukraine and fourth Ukraine becomes
permanently a neutral country and not an
anti anti-russia country how does this
process start I would say ideally with a
regime change in KF and the pro Russia
government coming to power so if Trump
is willing to give this to Putin then
the war will end
immediately so Will trump be willing to
give that and and even more pertinent
even if Trump is willing to give that to
to Putin will the US establishment allow
Trump to do that that's the question so
some things Trump could do I think the
economy is a easier easier task to some
extent some policies could could
alleviate the burden on the people the
inflationary burden ET on the people but
some things will take longer to change
so some things are easier some things
are really hard some are impossible I
don't think Putin I don't think Trump
can end the war even if he wants to the
US establishment W won't allow him to
end the war because they want the war
they have pushed Russia into the war
Putin started the war which means that
you blame you can blame him but he was
forced into it he had to do it to
safeguard his National
interest arush VMA says what do you
think about India's participation in the
head State Summit in Pakistan there's
the SEO Summit that's coming up the
pakistanis have invaded India they've
they've sent out an invitation to India
then obviously India will not
participate we refuse to engage with
Pakistan in any manner
whatsoever with good reason Pakistan is
a terrorist Nation we want to have
nothing to do with them so whenever the
SEO head of States heads of state Summit
happens Mr Modi won't
go to Pakistan no question about
it um at best we may send a
representative a low-level Junior
representative perhaps I'm not sure even
that would happen Visa Pakistan so
that's what I think and I think it's a
it's the right
decision Akash pingle says after coming
from Ukraine after coming back from
Ukraine to India Prime Minister Modi
called Biden and Putin what's going on
here look the visit to Ukraine by Prime
Minister Modi was merely a curtsy
visit there is no way to advance India's
national interest by engaging with
Ukraine by engaging with zinski and his
regime zalinski is a puppet of a foreign
power zinski is in power
undemocratically and uncon
constitutionally in Ukraine see
according to the Ukrainian Constitution
there should have been a general
election in
Ukraine by April or perhaps May March
April May somewhere around that time and
there was no general election and
zalinsky is still in power which means
he's in power illegally undemocratically
unconstitutionally and he's in power
only because the US has allowed him to
be in power so he's a puppet of a
foreign power and he has no real say
over the future of his Nation his nation
is being used as Canon F the people are
being used as Canon F and Ukraine is
devastated the econom is devastated
there's nothing India still stands to
gain by engaging with Ukraine so why did
Mr Modi go there just to uh balance
things out look we cannot afford to
uh make the superpower unhappy too much
we have obviously refused to participate
in the sanctions against Russia we have
a completely independent policy we are
buying tremendous amounts of oil from
Russia so let's kind of balance things
out by going to Ukraine in a symbolic
visit Cy visit putting your hand on on
zin's shoulder giving him a couple of
hugs and all what do we lose from that
what do we stand to lose nothing so
that's why Mr Modi went to Ukraine so he
comes back and then he speaks with Mr
Biden I don't know if it was Mr Biden or
or an EI clone of Biden but officially
it is said that Mr Modi spoke with Mr
Biden Biden has not been seen for quite
some time I don't even know if he is
still alive I'm not sure if he was alive
one year ago apparently there are lots
of body doubles of Biden every day his
appearance changes his height changes so
I think there are body doubles in play
when it comes to Biden but it doesn't
matter when you say that you spoke with
Biden it means that you spoke with the
US
government so Mr Modi apparently had a
call with somebody in the US government
it is said that it was Biden
and then a day or two later he speaks
with Mr Putin so what's going on here so
India is
playing a balancing
game India's
interests are we we have to safeguard
our interests and it is very clear that
the US doesn't want India to keep
growing the US wants to constrain
India's growth and constrain India as a
power
and it is very important for India not
to become too dependent on anyone Nation
so that's why we need to balance things
out the most powerful Nation apart from
the US is Russia we are on excellent
terms with Russia we need to keep that
going Mr Modi went to Ukraine at the
US's behest he spoke with Mr Biden or
whoever it was and then make sense to
speak with Mr Putin and and tell him
that listen Mr Putin we are definitely
not going to go against you and so on so
forth a bit of balancing especially for
a nation like India is important we want
a multi-polar world we don't want a
unipolar or bipolar World which will be
bad for the entire world so that's what
we're trying to do and that's why Mr
Modi makes it a point to engage with
every one of our important partners
geopolitical partners on a regular basis
and that's what this was all about
Balancing Act
okay vishak nay says what are the what
are the
steps how can a country become a 20
trillion economy from a $4 trillion
economy who has the authority to change
the systems in a country who has the
authority to change the
system whoever is powerful enough to
change it it is not easy to change a
system you need to be tremendously
powerful what does it mean to be
powerful it means you need to have a lot
of people who will do whatever you say
who will obey
you so in a democracy like India even if
you have more than 300 seats in
Parliament it typically means you got
about 30 40% of the vote which means 60%
of the vote at at least is against
you that's the kind of system we have so
even if you have 300 plus seats in
Parliament you aren't that
powerful people want obey
you so to for to be able to change the
systems in a country you need to be that
popular that powerful that more than
half the people of the nation will
definitely obey you and do what you say
in that case you can be in a position to
change the
systems otherwise nothing will change in
India so that's what it is now how can a
country become a 20 trillion economy
from $4 trillion economy how do you
become five times the size first of all
it takes takes time it'll take decades
please understand it'll take decades
secondly we have to reform the system
reduce the inefficiencies cut down on
the inefficiencies the inertia cut down
on whatever alleged corruption
exists and
focus
manufacturing focus on manufacturing
India has to become a manufacturing
power right now India is a service based
economy to a large extent services not
Manufacturing we export Services it and
whatnot we have to start exporting Goods
which means which means that we have to
start manufacturing
stuff doesn't matter what you
manufacture manufacture lots of stuff
stuff that people want and people need
and over time your technological
progress will definitely improve that's
how China did it when they started
Manufacturing in the 1980s they were at
a very low level of manufacturing
capability but over the dec they have
improved their technological PR now they
one of the most technological Advanced
nations in the world and they've done it
by having a clear long-term focus on
what technologies they want to acquire
what technologies they want to build
upon and uh for that you need a great
education system and they've done that
too they've invested trillions of
dollars worth of money into their
education system so we need to have a
long-term Focus we need to reform our
systems we need to reform the education
we need to focus on Manufacturing
and so many other things and obviously
we have to have good relations with
other countries especially the more
powerful countries we have to have good
relations with as many powerful
countries as
possible and ensure there is no war any
major military conflict over the next 20
30 years all of those things you have to
do which means you need to have great
leadership so yeah that's how you
transform a $4 trillion economy into a
20 trillion economy look if you look at
the history of the us over the 20th
century
from the 1950s onwards their economy
doubled in size every decade
roughly every decade every 10 years the
economy doubled in
size so if we can achieve that that sort
of growth then we could
become uh a 202 economy in less than 30
years if we can achieve that sort of
growth so right now we are at$ 4
trillion trillion
dollar if the next if by the by 2034 we
are 8 trillion
economy and by 2044 we are a $16
trillion economy then by
2050 or 2055 we could definitely
be a 20 plus trillion dollar economy so
it's take it takes time it's it takes a
lot of time but we have to do a lot of
things and and get a lot of things right
for this to happen so yeah that's the
road ahead if everything goes right for
us
okay okay editor 47 says I'm a 10th
grader I want to pursue the humanities
as a career and I don't want to be a
liability on my parents where they have
to pay my Hefty College fees what path
would you suggest me
what I would urge you to ask yourself is
let's say you pursue the humanities as a
career okay once you get your
degree what are you going to produce for
the
country and and what kind of career path
do you have going forward once you get
your degree see generally every citizen
has to be a productive member of
society right and if you acquire a
degree or any skill
it has to produce
something which society
needs with a degree in the humanities
let say
sociology or
whatever your degree is relevant and
useful if you go into if you have a
research career and you do some research
but if you don't have a research career
and you then what what is your
degree going to give you that will be
productive in life
that's something you have to ask
yourself so what I'm saying is you have
to ask yourself after you get your
degree what is the kind of career path
you want to have do you want to be a
professor do you want to be a university
Professor University college
professor do you want to be a researcher
somewhere in some Institute because with
a Humanities degree that's what you can
do or you will have
to uh start a career in some company and
acquire skills from scratch which have
nothing to do with the humanities so
that is one thing you to ask yourself
and secondly
um generally people who have Humanities
degrees uh what's what's the chance of
them getting a great job good job high
paying job I'm not really
sure
um so what I'm trying to say in this
very strange roundabout manner is
Humanities are a waste of time
unfortunately
look with a degree in the humanities you
don't you not equipped to produce
anything useful for the country and for
society but if if that is what you are
best at then you would need after
getting your degree to pursue a research
career or an academic career in order to
make use of the degree
so if if that's the path that you think
is best for yourself then I would say go
for that career and obviously if you
don't want to be a liability for your
par parents where you where they have to
pay a hefty College fee what do you do
about
that then you need to have money of your
own which means you need to do some job
part-time or whatever but in India you
don't have part-time jobs and they don't
pay really well so I think until you
have a career of your own you're going
to be dependent on your
parents I'm sure there must be some
institutions that offer scholarships to
students do we have that in India I'm
not
sure um but the reality is that for most
Indian
students you're going to have to depend
on your parents as long as you're a
student because you have no job and your
no money of your own the best you can do
is that once you have acquired your
degree and your education is over you
get a high paying
job and
hopefully pay back to your parents
whatever they spend on your education
that's the best thing but I am not a big
fan of humanities because they produce
nothing for the country
actually unfortunately there's so much
scope for the Humanities in terms of
research India is a is a potential gold
mine for sociological research Etc but
most sociology departments if not
all don't do any research and whatever
research they do is actually something
that is is aimed
at maligning the country in a in a
variety of ways so that's the
problem
okay Ganesh Kumar says I'm living in
Canada for 12 years seeing a sharp
decline of Standards dollar value health
care jobs and housing given the global
situation and Wars would you say it's a
no-brainer to come
back yeah if you if you look at the
situation a decade before today then
Canada was a very enticing place if for
anybody who wanted to move out of India
you know health care and jobs and all
that living standards quality of life
all that today things have changed
significantly Mr tudo has made a mess of
Canada the economy and everything
overall the housing crisis is a big big
problem uh so for you as an individual
as a person it's going to be an
individual decision not a global
geopolitical decision that Canada is
doing not very great and there's a war
in Ukraine so because of that should I
go back to India no if you have a good
job wherever you are in Canada it pays
you well and you have reasonably good
living standards then as an individual
it makes sense to stay where you are and
if you have good career prospects in
Canada and you will do better than let's
say the majority of the population then
it makes sense to stay in
can on an individual level okay as a as
a purely selfish
individual but if you are being affected
by the economic scenario if you don't
have good career prospects if the amount
of money you're earning doesn't give
give you a good lifestyle then maybe it
makes sense to return to India as as
long as you will get a better lifestyle
and a better career in India so you have
to weigh up all these possible scenarios
and possible
outcomes before you make a choice so I
don't think it's a no-brainer it depends
on your specific individual situation so
you're going to have to calculate these
things and arrive at a logical decision
based on pure logic and numbers and your
future growth path which you could
achieve in this country or that that's
how we make the
decision
okay
um indrajit says nuclear winter o what
would the world be like and how would
people live during nuclear winter
hypothetically so what's a nuclear
winter so I'm sure no one remembers it
because no one was around but there was
an impact
event about 66 million years ago okay
the chub impact event you want to see
where it is uh let me show you yukatan
Peninsula
Mexico here's Mexico and here is yukatan
okay and if you look at um yukatan then
there is the city of Merida and there's
the town of chi shub
here this town chalub is the is roughly
the epicenter of that impact event the
impact was an asteroid which slammed
into the into the Earth and and there's
this massive underground crater that you
can detect if you have the means of
doing so Chulo so that impact event
killed off it triggered a mass
extinction on the planet it killed off
the nonavian dinosaurs and lots of other
species on the planet our ancestors the
little mammals they survived which is
why we are here and the Aven dinosaurs
also survived which is why we have birds
out there dinosaurs still exist they're
Birds but the rest of these
species went extinct especially the
large ones the large species the
dinosaurs big ones so that's kind of a
nuclear winter scenario so now that we
understand that
so so what happened when this object
this asteroid slammed into the
planet massive explosion gigantic
explosion millions of times the um
energy output of the Hiroshima nuclear
test and a tremendous amount of of suit
of dust of carbon of of all that of
vaporized Rock Etc was thrown up into
the atmosphere and it completely crowded
the atmosphere and there was no sunlight
direct sunlight on the planet for about
a decade roughly give or take so when
there is no sunlight plants die because
plants get their energy and food through
the process of photosynthesis which
requires light sunlight if there is no
light plants die if the plants die
herbivorous animals die if herbivorous
animals die the carnivorous animals that
eat those herbivorous animals they also
die so what's left only the little
little beings are able to somehow
survive until sunlight returns and then
things go back to over time to
normal a nuclear winter scenario is very
similar to that so how does a nuclear
winter happen and what does it look like
a nuclear winter
happens if there is a massive nuclear
exchange involving hundreds or thousands
of nuclear Warheads so hundreds or even
thousands of nuclear
explosions these explosions will VAP
every nuclear explosion on the surface
or near the near the surface it
vaporizes part of the Earth's surface a
small amount of the Earth's surface it
throws up a tremendous amount of debris
into the
atmosphere vaporized rock dust and all
kinds of other very small particles and
if you have thousands of these or
hundreds or even thousands of these then
it will recreate the chick Shob impact
scenario the whole planet is shrouded in
darkness there is no sunlight for months
even
years what does that do very rapid
climate change very rapid in like matter
of days all the heat disappears snow
everywhere ice everywhere everything is
frozen most people living in the
tropical regions will die in a matter of
hours those who survive may not last a
week or
two then there is a immediate shortage
of food all your livestock animals start
dying all the trees start dying all the
forests start dying and then who
survives maybe 1% 2% of humanity
survives after a month or two after a
year that is the incredible disaster
that nuclear winter is how will people
live I wonder how they will live
everything will be frozen there'll be no
light there'll be no food sources
telecommunications gone satellites no
longer work electricity doesn't
exist communication Supply chains all
gone tray
over Nations no longer exist populations
decimated so if anyone survives it's
going to be like one or 2% of
humanity it is going to be an Extinction
event most species on the planet of
animals fish Etc will die out that is
what a nuclear winter is maybe Humanity
could could go extinct if this happens
so that is why a nuclear war is an
unthinkable Unthinkable disaster we
never want it to
happen that's how bad it is that's how
bad nuclear winter is it most likely
leads to the extinction of humanity
itself life will not disappear from the
planet life will
continue after a year or two after 5
years whatever sunlight Rec returns to
the planet depending on how many nuclear
warheads were were used sunlight will
eventually return and some life will
persist and then it will start thriving
again after decades centuries whatever
and new species will will emerge but we
who did this most likely won't survive
so that's why you know n World War I and
nuclear war it's it's it's the last
thing we
want last thing we want it's not a
joke suar says what do you think how
will the earth end nukes War climate
disaster
Etc no you asking about the end of
humanity not the end of end end of the
planet I'll tell you what is the end of
the planet Earth it's about 5 billion
years from now
about 5 billion years from now roughly
the sun will become a red super giant
its outer layers of the sun the star the
outer layers will expand expand expand
the diameter will increase and
eventually the sun its outermost layers
will engulf our planet and we will
become part of the sun we will become
inside the Sun that is what will end the
Earth so that is how the Earth ends
about 5 billion years from now the real
question you're trying to ask is how
will Humanity
end I hope it never ends I hope five
billion years from now whatever our
descendants look like they have moved on
to a different star system or
wherever but how could Humanity end if
we are not careful definitely nuclear
war if we are not careful we could
trigger nuclear war which would end
Humanity uh so conventional War could
also decimate a large portion of
humanity but I think it's nuclear war
that is real danger climate disaster I
don't think so climate change is a real
thing of course a real thing climate
change has always
existed the earth's climate is always
been changing and today is not different
and some amount of the climate change we
are seeing is caused by Humanity no
doubt but I think we will be able to
adapt and evolve in the future the Earth
may get hotter than what it is now
several degrees which means it will
reconfigure the entire geographical
dimension of the earth low-lying areas
could get swallowed by the oceans with
the rise of the ocean levels and so on
and it'll cause a lot of hardship to
humanity but it will not end Humanity
Humanity will still continue it is
nuclear war that is the most immediate
and most dangerous scariest scenario and
of course
pandemics are a real threat natural or
engineered whatever and
uh Water Crisis
Etc Health
crisis microplastics in the brain and
other tissues and all that there's a lot
of things that can go wrong especially
because of the way we have treated the
planet but I think the scariest scenario
that could end humanity is is nuclear
war nuclear
winter which is why I always keep saying
we don't ever want to see World War I
which means nuclear war between the most
powerful Nations we don't want
that omit Singh
says is mathematics invented or
discovered look mathematics what is
mathematics mathematics is
essentially the representation in
symbolic
language of the patterns and
regularities that underly the Universe
the natural world that that's what
mathematics is so these the there are
these regularities and patterns in the
natural world in the universe and the
representative representation of those
regularities and patterns in symbolic
language is
mathematics now so with that
understood it's clearly something
we discover right yes so mathematics is
discovered but some is invented for
example if you want to solve certain
families of equations you have to invent
new techniques for doing that so that is
invented isn't it you to invent
techniques for Sol for for for
differentiation for integration for
solving differential equations for
solving linear equations all kinds of
techniques have to be
invented and uh you could invent
different kinds of techniques to achieve
the same end
results so some of it so so those
techniques are
invented but mathematics itself is
discovered so it's kind of both that's
how I see
it deep Ahuja says to strengthen India's
defense should India acquire the Su 57
Suk 57 aircraft felon from Russia which
has better capabilities instead of
working on its own AMC jet which will
take a long time to come in service
look if the Su 57 is really as good as
people say buy a number of those if if
we
really are pressed for
time but even if we purchase that
aircraft the entire trial process blah
blah blah the bureaucratic red tap
procedure will take I don't know
years and then once the deal is signed
the Russians F to produce those
aircraft they also have a requirement
for those aircraft now if they have to
produce X number of them for India they
have to that takes time
so the whole process could anyway take a
decade it's not like those those
aircraft are sitting our fruits ripe
fruits on a tree is go and pluck them
off it's not how it is and then our
wonderful process will say that we have
certain specific India specific
requirements for the isuka 57 we want so
and so thing and not this thing and that
thing you need to change and bl and then
the process drags even
further so I would say that if we are
really in if you really need a certain
number of aircraft very
fast it's fine to buy those maybe the
the Gaal which is a very good plane or
if you want a better one and if the Su
is better 57 then get a number of those
maybe 100 200
whatever but we cannot stop working on
our homegrown Technologies which is
committing metaphorical
suicide we need to in the long run be
able to produce everything in
house because that's the only way to be
genuinely Sovereign if you are depending
on other nations for your vital needs
and requirements you are not fully
Sovereign it's a question of
sovereignty you lack Independence if
you're dependent on on other nations for
these vital needs because then they can
arm twist you then they can make you
dance to their Tunes I'm not saying the
Russians will do that but why give
anybody the
opportunity so we should keep on working
on the amca jet on the various variants
of the Tes on whatever else we're
working on whether people know or not we
should keep working on all those things
we should keep working on the indigenous
jet engine technology but yes if
required we can purchase a number of
aircraft from the French from the
Russians or whoever is a stop Gap
measure as long as it does not infringe
on our sovereignty you buy things from
the Americans it's going to poke holes
into your
sovereignty so better do it from the
French or the Russians but you cannot
compromise on your indigenous programs
we had the marut fighter plane in the
60s 70s we killed it
our what's the correct word what's the
our wonderful magnificent
leaders killed the Maru fighter plane
it was an underpower underpowered
fighter plane because it had inferior
jet engines the fighter plane design was
superb if we had not killed off that
fighter plane fighter
jet fighter plane program by today we
would have had a whole family of
different kinds of fighter planes based
on the marut and those aircraft would
have been some of the best in the world
so you understand so today if we have
the Tes which is a reasonably good
fighter plane we should continue on that
they just Mark Mark whatever mark one 1
a mark 2 whatever and the amca just keep
building keep iterating keep Mak making
better aircraft we it is extremely
important vitally important for our
future Generations that we have
technology of our own that we don't have
to depend on
others for
okay
um where is that one second okay let's
take this one feminist Slayer says is it
wrong to take motivation from anime
characters when a person doesn't have
any role model in your life is it good
to be selfish sometimes look if you
don't have a role model in your life you
can certainly take motivation from your
favorite fictional
characters anime characters are also
fictional characters so I can give other
examples if
you uh there are lots of people who are
fans of the lot of the
Rings and that has many great characters
Aragon gandal whatever those are not
real people they never existed but you
find those characteristics great if you
find them inspiring certainly those are
archetypes of human traits
you can certainly take inspiration from
that and similarly you can take you can
definitely take motivation inspiration
whatever from anime characters if that
works for you absolutely nothing wrong
with that what you are being inspired by
and motivated by is a number is a set of
human traits that you find attractive
and
inspiring and that certainly can come
from a fictional character so nothing
wrong with that absolutely
none is it good to be selfish sometimes
well
yeah you then you you cannot be selfless
at all
times it is certainly fine to be selfish
look there will be times when people
will take advantage of you in life
people will
uh yeah they will they will exploit you
at times that's the nature of the world
most people are like that okay um so you
will find yourself in such situations at
various points in your life and at such
times it is important to be selfish and
put yourself first and at the end of the
day please realize that the main
character in your life is you other
people will come and go you will watch
ask abijit for I don't know whatever
number of episodes and someday you will
move on to something
else so the main character in your life
is you everybody else comes and goes but
you are with yourself
forever so you certainly must put
yourself first first if you want to be
selfless first transform yourself into a
person of substance genuine substance
and you cannot do that without placing
yourself first for a certain number of
years and working on yourself and
prioritizing your interests and needs
over those of others and then when you
are
sufficiently significantly substantial
person you can be selfless and you will
have a much more impact on the word
by waiting until that time so it is
certainly good to be
selfish not at times most times but then
when you want to be selfless do be so
strategically in a way that genuinely is
impactful to the
world okay I think we are almost at the
end of
things Arian Knight says do you watch
Italian or French movies I've seen all
kinds of movies I actually speak French
I understand French so um yeah I do
these days I don't watch any movies
unfortunately but I've seen many French
movies uh yeah one of my favorite actors
when I was a kid was Jean Paul Bondo I
don't know if he's still alive great
actor so I've seen French movies I've
seen some Italian movies I've seen those
1960s 7s movies and
all but these days I don't I don't watch
any I have no idea what's being what's
coming out of France and Italy these
days they used to have great movies back
in the day
like before my time you know 60s 70s etc
those are classic movies but these days
I have no idea what's going out
hopefully they're still doing better
compared to the rest of the
West
[Music]
okay tanos banery is says is it possible
that Isaac Newton was referring to
Indians when he said I stand on the
shoulders of giants on the shoulders of
giants because the height of Indians was
gigantic up to a few centuries ago what
evidence do we have that Indians were
giants like genuinely gigantic what
evidence do we have no you if you make a
claim that Indians were gigantic until a
few centuries ago what is the
evidence a claim has to be based on
evidence I have personally seen no
evidence that Indians were gigantic I'm
aware of skeletons from the ganga Valley
region from about 30,000 years ago where
the average height of the person was
about 6 feet tall
but that is not gigantic that is tall
but reasonably tall it's not gigantic
gigantic is like 8 NT tall there is
absolutely zero evidence hard evidence
of Indians being 8 N9 10 feet tall I
have not seen a single piece of evidence
so I don't think he was refering to that
okay Newton was refering to people
without refering to them standing on the
shoulders of giants means the scientists
who came before him and did the
groundwork that he used in making his
discoveries that's what he was referring
to most likely and probably he was
probably he was making a dig at Robert
Hook his his great
rival you know there is no portrait that
still survives of Robert
Hook it's because Einstein was oh sorry
it's because Newton was jealous of
Robert Hook and he had his portraits
removed from the Royal Society and
whatnot yeah even great people can be
Petty at times okay with that done uh we
have we at the end of today's session
thank you so much for all the questions
and I apologize to all those of you
whose questions I could not take her Z I
understand he means Indian scientific
knowledge he was talking about gigantic
people and there is no evidence that
Newton was referring to Indians even in
the terms of scientific knowledge anyway
anyway anyway so thank you so much for
your questions I will take another live
stream tomorrow in which I will take a
number of questions from the comments
and then we will do some questions from
the live chat as well so please uh do
come do participate uh yes I have seen
Gladiator good
movie all right so that's it for today
and uh I will see you in tomorrow's live
stream thank you so much and do keep
raising your standards at all times keep
asking questions of me and of yourselves
as well thank you and I'll see you in
tomorrow's live stream bye